大家早上好，我叫 Gustaf，在 Y Combinator（YC）工作，
Good morning, everyone. My name is Gustaf and I work here at Y Combinator
担任 group partner。
as a group partner.
我从 2017 年就在这里了。
I've been here since 2017.
加入 YC 之前，我在 Airbnb 做 product lead，其实我在 2007 年也是一名 YC 创始人。
Before YC, I was a product lead at Airbnb and actually a YC founder back in 2007.
今天我要讲的是，如何和你的用户以及未来的客户交谈。
Today, I'm going to talk about how to talk to your users and your future customers.
这是我今天打算讲的内容。
Here's what I plan to cover today.
第一，为什么最好的创始人会在公司的整个生命周期里持续和用户交谈。
Why the best founders talk to the users throughout the lifetime of the company.
第二，如何找到你的用户，以及如何和他们交谈。第三，
2. How to find your users and how to talk to them. 3.
该问他们什么问题，不该问什么问题。第四，
What questions to ask them and what not to ask them. And 4.
如何把你的结论变成一个 MVP（最小可行产品）。
How to turn your conclusions into an MVP.
世界上大多数人对新创业公司如何诞生的理解，
Most people in the world have the idea on how new startups are formed.
完全是错的。他们以为新产品的点子，是创始人随手
Completely wrong. They think ideas of new products is something the founders just
就想出来的，
come up with on a
也许是在某个慵懒的周日，或者深夜写代码的时候？
lazy Sunday or a late night coding session?
你大概知道，事情并不是这样的。
You probably know it doesn't work this way.
你们看到的这个画面，是电影 The Social Network（社交网络）里的一幕。
This scene, as you can see here, is a scene from the Social Network movie.
这是部好电影，但它在 Facebook 到底怎么起步这件事上搞错了很多。
It's a great movie, but they got a lot of things wrong on how Facebook actually got started.
这位是 Brian Chesky。Brian 是 Airbnb 的联合创始人兼 CEO。
This is Brian Chesky. Brian is the co founder and CEO of Airbnb.
照片左边这位是 Amol。
On the left side of the photo is Amol.
Amol 是 Airbnb 上的第一位房客。
Amol was the very first guest on Airbnb.
在 Airbnb 刚上线的时候，他们真的一起在旧金山度过了一个周末。
They actually spent a weekend together in San Francisco when Airbnb kind of launched.
你注意到这张照片和上一张的区别了吗？
You notice the difference between this photo and the previous photo? Well,
这张照片是真实的照片，
this photo actually is a real photo
里面包含了和一位真实客户的双向对话。
and includes a two way conversation with a real customer.
优秀的创始人在还没有产品的时候，就会和未来的客户交谈。
Great founders talk to future customers before they even have a product.
事实上，世界上最好的创始人，会直接向他们的用户学习，
In fact, the very best founders in the world Learned a directly from their users
贯穿公司的整个生命周期。好好体会这一点。
throughout the life of their company. Let that sink in.
如果你正确地找到了谁是你的用户，
If you have correctly identified who your users are,
你就应该在公司的整个生命周期里向他们学习。
you should learn from them throughout the lifetime of your company.
你也许会问为什么，因为用户和客户会让你保持诚实。
Why you might ask, users and customers will keep you honest.
他们是唯一真正付钱给你的利益相关者。
They are the only stakeholders actually paying you anything.
如果有谁会跟你说真话，那一定是他们。
If anyone will tell you the truth, it will be them.
所以我今天要讲的，就是如何把这件事做好。
So my talk today is about how to do this well.
我们再来讲一个 Airbnb 的故事。
So let's talk about another Airbnb story.
2010 年，我自己都记得这件事，Airbnb 的 CEO Brian Chesky
In 2010, and I remember this myself, Brian Chesky, the CEO of Airbnb,
决定做一个实验。
he'll decide to launch an experiment.
他打算放弃自己的公寓，
He was going to give up his apartment
在接下来的几个月里，住进 50 个不同的 Airbnb 房源。
and live in 50 different Airbnbs over the next couple of months.
你可能会想，谁会去做这种事？太麻烦了。
You might ask yourself, why would anyone do that? So much hassle.
大多数读到这个实验相关文章的人（因为他确实公开宣布了），
Most people who read the articles about this experiment, because he did announce it,
都没抓住重点。
they missed the point.
我个人记得当时觉得这挺疯狂的。
I personally remember this being kind of crazy.
通过这样做，Brian 能真真切切地和这 50 位
By doing this, Brian will literally get a chance to talk to every one of these 50
房东交谈，在旅途中的每一天。
hosts each single day on his trip.
这对你的产品来说，是多么难得的诚实反馈来源。
And what an incredible source of honest feedback on your product.
没有 Airbnb 的房东，就没有今天的 Airbnb。
Without the Airbnb hosts, Airbnb would not exist. Exist today.
Brian、Joe 和 Nate 很早就做到的一件事，是深入理解房东的动机
What Brian, Joe and Nate did so early is deeply understand the motivations.
以及他们的反馈。直到今天，
And the feedback from their hosts. Still today,
Brian 和 Joe 仍会接到房东打到他们私人手机上的电话。
Brian and Joe gets calls from hosts on their personal cell phone numbers.
我记得我在 Airbnb 上班的第一天，他们就跟我说了这件事。
I remember them telling me that on the first day I worked at Airbnb.
他们为什么这么做？因为那是他们早期放在网站上，
Why do they do that? Well, it's the number that they put on the website
并分享给所有房东的号码。
and share with all of their hosts early on.
他们没有躲在匿名邮箱后面。
They weren't hiding behind anonymous email.
他们想听到客户的声音。
They wanted to hear from the customers.
在当时，这看起来几乎是很激进的。
At the time, this seemed almost radical.
大多数创始人会把时间花在电脑前，试图找到
Most founders would spend their time in front of the computers trying to find
像 Google Ads 这样可扩展的增长渠道。不幸的是，
scalable growth channels like Google Ads. Unfortunately,
大多数创始人至今仍没有和用户建立起私人联系。
most founders still don't build personal connections with their users.
如今，他们躲在 info@ 邮箱，或者 do-not-reply 邮箱后面。
Today, they hide behind info at emails or don't do not reply emails.
不信？你只要在自己的邮箱里搜一下 do-not-reply@
You don't believe me? You should just do a search in your email for do not reply at
看看有多少人不愿意和自己的客户聊。
and see how many people don't want to talk to their customers.
那我们先从搞清楚该和谁聊开始。
So let's start by trying to figure out who I should talk to.
访谈你认识的人或者你人脉圈里的人总是最容易的。
It's always easy to interview people that you know or people who are in your network.
他们只是最有可能回应你。
They're simply the most likely to respond,
但为了不冒犯你，他们的回答可能没那么诚实。
but perhaps can be less honest in their answers to not offend you.
别害怕去联系他们，也别害怕被拒绝。
Don't be afraid of reaching out to them and don't be afraid of rejection.
第二类人是同事或前同事。
The second group here is co-workers or former co-workers.
他们可以是非常好的信息来源。
They can be a really great source.
他们可能对这个话题很了解，如果你是在为创业公司做软件，
They might know the topic really well and if you're building software for startups,
你就能轻松找到一个潜在用户。
you can easily navigate yourself to someone who's a potential user.
还有一种很常见的情况，你聊的早期用户在你的个人
It's also very common that the early users you speak to are outside of your personal
圈子或同事圈子之外。
circles or your co-worker circles.
当问到 YC 创始人是怎么找到早期用户的，
When asking YC founders how they found their early users,
最常见的一些答案是 LinkedIn、Reddit 论坛、
some of the most common answers were LinkedIn, Reddit forums,
Slack 或 Discord 社区，有时还有线下活动。
Slack or discord communities, and sometimes in person events.
为了更好地说明这个过程，我要开一家新的模拟创业公司。
So to illustrate this process a little better, I'm going to start a new mock startup.
这不是真实的公司，只是我编出来的。
This is not a real company. I'm just making it up.
但我会像对待真实公司一样走一遍整个流程。
But I'm going to go through the process as I would have if this was a real company.
首先，我想搞清楚这个问题是不是真实存在的。
And first, I want to understand if the problem is real.
我这里有一个假设，
My hypothesis that I have here,
有点像我们在 YC 有时说的“想法空间”，
or kind of like the idea space that we sometimes call at YC,
就是企业想减少自己的碳排放，
is that companies want to reduce their carbon emissions,
但因为种种原因没有去做。所以我的计划很简单。
but for whatever reasons don't do that. So my plan is very simple.
第一，我想先访谈一些潜在客户。第二，
I want to first interview some potential customers. 2.
了解围绕碳排放的问题和动机；第三，
Learn about the problems and motivations around carbon emissions and 3,
试着搞清楚 MVP 会是什么样子。MVP 就是最小可行产品。
try to understand what an MVP will look like. MVP is a minimal viable product.
为了做这个调研，我打算先去联系创始人、CEO、
To do this research, I plan to start by reaching out to founders, CEOs,
以及创业公司的 CFO。
CFOs at startups.
或者更大的公司。
Or bigger companies.
我还会在 LinkedIn 上联系一些人，
I'm also going to reach out to people on LinkedIn
他们的头衔里带有 carbon、climate 或 sustainability 这类词，
that have titles like carbon or climate or sustainability,
基本上就是能提示我他们可能值得聊的词。
basically words that gives me a hint that they might be relevant people to talk to.
那我想了解什么呢？首先，我想搞清楚，
So what am I looking to learn? Well, first, I'm trying to understand,
他们所在的公司在不在意自己的碳排放？
do the company that they work for care about their carbon emissions?
第二，如果在意，为什么在意；如果不在意，又为什么不在意？
And 2, why do they care and why do they not care if they don't care?
第三，公司里谁可能最在意这件事，为什么？
And 3, who in that company might be the one who cares the most about this and why?
好，这里有两个联系信息的例子。
All right, so, so here are two examples of outreach messages.
第一个是发给一位曾在 Airbnb 共事过的 CFO 的 LinkedIn 消息。
So the first one is a LinkedIn message to a CFO who I used to work with at Airbnb.
消息大概是这样，首先我做自我介绍。
The message will go something like this, first, I introduce myself.
我提一下我们在 Airbnb 共事的经历。
I mention something about our time at Airbnb.
然后我说我在做一个新项目，简单描述一下，
Then I say I'm starting a new project. Briefly describe it,
但不要太详细，
but not too much in detail,
然后就约一个 20 分钟的电话或视频通话。
and I just ask for a 20 minute phone call or a video call.
就这样。这是另一个例子，发给一个我不认识的人。
That's it. And here's another example of a message to someone I don't know.
同样是在 LinkedIn 上，发给我之前提到的那类人。
It's also on LinkedIn to the same group that I mentioned earlier.
内容类似，但针对的是我不认识的人。
It's similar but geared towards people I don't know.
所以消息和语气都会稍有不同。
So the message will and the tone will be a little bit different.
好，一旦我接通电话或视频，
All right, so one, once I get on the phone or once I get on the video call,
我们来聊聊怎么真正去访谈潜在客户。
let's talk about how to actually interview potential customers.
首先，你要确保这些访谈是通过视频通话、
So first you want to make sure that these interviews are over video calls,
电话或者面对面进行的。
phone calls or in person.
五分钟的视频访谈能让你学到的，远比 500 份甚至 5000 份问卷回答还多。
You can learn a lot more from a five minute video interview than 500 or 5000 survey responses.
其次，你要和受访者建立一些融洽的关系。
Secondly, you want to build some rapport with the interviewee.
他们要回答的问题，
They're going to give you answers to questions
可能之前从没有人问过他们。
that maybe no one has asked them before.
所以你要确保他们能信任你，
So you need to make sure that they can trust you
并且在这种情境下感到自在。
and feel comfortable in this situation.
接下来，这里最重要的一点，最最
Next, the most important thing here, the most, most,
重要的一点，就是不要过早介绍你的想法，最好等到通话
most important thing here is to not introduce your idea till maybe at the end of the
快结束时再说，甚至干脆不说，太早说会让他们的回答产生偏差。
call or maybe not at all, doing this too early can bias them in their answers.
你在这次访谈里的角色是倾听，而不是说话。
Your role here in this interview is to listen, not to talk.
有一些很好的技巧，能让人愿意敞开心扉，
There are some great techniques to get people to open up
谈谈他们遇到的问题。
and talk about their problems.
其中一个好方法，就是提开放式的追问。
And one good one is to ask follow up questions that are open ended.
比如“跟我说说那件事”。如果你不录下这次访谈，
For example, tell me about that. If you're not recording the interview,
至少也要尽可能多做笔记。
you should at least take notes as much as you can.
反正你迟早要把录音整理成笔记，
You need to translate the recordings to notes anyway,
所以不如在访谈现场就直接记笔记。
so you might as well take notes in the in the actual interview.
我这里放一个示例视频，演示我这家碳排放公司的一位潜在客户，
I'm gonna play an example video here on how a potential customer for my carbon
以及那段对话会是什么样子。嗨，你好吗？
emission company and how that conversation would go like, hi, how are you?
自从我们在 Airbnb 一起共事，已经很久了。是啊，很高兴见到你。
It's been a long time since we worked together at Airbnb. Yeah, great to see you.
不知道我有没有跟你说过，我在考虑再创办一家公司，
So I don't know if I told you this, but I'm thinking about starting another company,
我有几个问题想问问你，关于这个我感兴趣的领域。
and I have a couple questions I wanted to ask you about this area
呃，你们公司 Monteview Inc，
that I'm interested in. Uh, does your company, Monteview Inc,
你们在意自己的碳排放吗？
do you care about your carbon emissions?
我们确实在意，我们请了一位顾问，每年做一份 PDF 报告。
We do actually care, and we use a consultant who creates these PDF reports once a year.
有意思。呃，那份报告你们拿来做什么？
Interesting. Uh, what do you do with a report?
我是说，很遗憾，目前我们其实没怎么根据它采取行动。
I mean, right now I don't think we really take much action on it, unfortunately.
什么？为什么不呢？
What? Why not?
就是很难知道那些信息该怎么用。
It's just really hard to know what to do with the information.
那些信息太密集了，还用了一些我们看不太懂的词。
The information is really dense and uses words we don't really understand.
跟我多说说这个。
Tell me more about that.
是这样，我们请了这位顾问。
Well, we hired this consultant.
他们让我们在一个 Word 文档里填写信息，
They asked us to fill out this word DOC with information,
但里面填进去的很多数据，呃，好像并不准确。
but much of the data that goes into it, uh, seems inaccurate.
我就觉得我们还得再找个专家，来搞清楚这些数据该怎么用。
And I just feel like we need another expert to figure out what to do with the data.
明白，明白。呃，但对你们公司来说，追踪碳排放到底为什么重要？
Got it. Got it. Um, but why is it important for your company at all to track carbon emission?
是这样，我们的客户一直在问我们的排放情况，我们的银行也在问，
Well, our customers have been asking about our emissions and so has our bank
就是我们想申请新贷款的时候。
when we try to get new loans.
呃，我觉得还有一些法规也快出台了。
Um, and I think there's some regulations coming up, too.
你注意到了吗，我自始至终都没有介绍产品或解决方案。
You notice here how I never introduced a product or a solution.
我只是提问，去了解 Amy 遇到的问题。
I only ask questions to learn about the problem that Amy is having.
我甚至都没说我打算做什么产品。
I don't even say what I'm going to build.
你就应该这么做。这里有一些非常具体的问题，
That's how you want to do it. Here are some very specific questions
可以用在你的访谈里。
that you can use in your interviews.
1. 跟我说说你现在是怎么做 X 的。X 当然是指某个具体的问题、某个任务，
1. Tell me how you do X today. By X, of course, I'm referring to a specific problem, a task,
或者你想实现的某个目标。2.
or a goal that you are trying to solve. 2.
在做 X 这件事上，最难的是什么？3.
What is the hardest thing you are doing about X? 3.
为什么难？4. 你多久要做一次 X？5.
Why is it hard? 4. How often do you have to do X? 5.
对你们公司来说，做 X 为什么重要？
Why is it important for your company to do X?
一定要把这个问题深挖下去。
Make sure you dive deep into this question.
理解他们的动机在这里会非常关键。
Like understanding their motivation is going to be critical here.
6. 你现在是怎么自己解决这个问题的？
And 6, what do you do to solve this problem for yourself today?
弄清楚他们实际在做什么，非常重要。
It's really important to understand what they're doing.
如果你能亲眼看着他们操作，那就更好了。
Now, if you can watch them do this, that's even better.
如果他们能在视频通话里共享屏幕，或者在访谈时给你看他们的电脑，
If they can screen share during the video call or show you their laptop
让你看看他们实际是怎么拿到那份 PDF 报告的，
as you're doing the interview and show you how they actually get the PDF report,
他们拿它做什么，它长什么样。
what they do with it, how it looks like.
那是最理想的状态。你要深入理解他们的行为，
That's the ideal state. You want to deeply understand their behavior,
不只是他们说了什么，而是他们做了什么，
not just what they're saying but what they're doing,
因为改变行为会很难。
because changing the behavior will be hard.
你也可以做追问，请一定学会怎么用好这些问题。
You can also ask follow up questions and please learn how to make use of these ones.
很难指望别人在一个问题的一个回答里就把一切都说清楚。
It's very hard to get someone to say everything in just one answer to one question.
要习惯多问这样的问题，比如“你这么说是什么意思？”
Get comfortable with asking questions like, what do you mean by that?
或者“你能多说说吗？”，又或者“这对你为什么重要？”
Or can you tell me more about that or why is that important to you?
这里有一些你不该问的问题。比如说，
Here are some questions that you should not ask. Like,
有些做法会让访谈偏离正轨。
there are ways you can kind of derail this interview.
“你会用我们的产品吗？”
Will you use our product?
他们大概率会说会，
They're probably going to say yes,
但那个回答对你其实毫无价值。
but they're not going to mean anything to you in that answer.
第二，哪些功能能让产品 X 变得更好？
Two, which features would make product X better?
记住，用户的任务是告诉你问题所在。
Remember, their job is to tell you about the problem.
你的任务是思考用哪些功能来解决这个问题。
Your job is to think about what features to solve that problem.
所以让他们做你该做的事，其实帮不了你。
So asking them about your job isn't really going to help you.
是非题对你来说也没太大帮助。
Yes and no questions, that's not really that helpful for you.
你希望他们展开讲，给你尽可能多的具体、真实的例子。
You want them to explain and give you as many concrete and real examples as possible.
所以只是简单地问是非题并不理想。
So just simply asking yes no questions is not ideal here.
第四，在你看来，更好的产品 X 会是什么样？
And 4, how would a better product X look like to you?
在你看来，更好的碳排放统计软件会是什么样？
How would a better carbon emission counting software look like to you?
很多用户不是产品开发者，也不是软件工程师。
Many of the people aren't product developers. They're not software engineers.
他们不是设计师。
They're not designers.
他们不是产品经理，这不是他们的工作。
They're not product managers. This is not their job.
他们的工作是另一回事。
Their job is to do a different job.
是你在努力理解他们工作中难在哪里。
You are the one trying to understand what is the challenging part about their job.
最后，同时问两个问题会让他们困惑。
And finally asking two questions at the same time, it's going to confuse them.
也会让你得到的答案变得混乱。
It's going to confuse your answers.
当你急着想要答案时，很容易犯这个毛病，
So this is when you're eager to get, get answers, it's very easy to do this,
但要尽量避免。
this thing, but try to avoid it.
不过我想强调我这里提到的其中一点。
But I want to highlight one of the things I mentioned here.
访谈中有一个很大的风险，
There's one big danger during interviews,
那就是只关注功能，而不是问题。
and that is to focus on features instead of problems.
你很自然会这么做。
It's very natural for you to do that.
你的大脑在想各种解决这个问题的办法。
Your brain is thinking through all the ways you're going to solve this problem.
但你在这次访谈里真正要做的，是深入理解
But really what you're here for during this interview is to deeply understand the
问题，而不是想出解决方案。那是留给
problems, not actually come up with solutions. That's for.
另一个环节的。用户通常能提出好问题，
For a separate event. So users generally have good problems,
但给出的解决方案通常很糟。
but also generally bad solutions.
我举两个具体例子。Gmail 早期，
So I'll give you two specific examples. So early days of Gmail,
用户要求 Gmail 的创始人 Paul Buchheit，
users were asking Paul Buchheit, the founder of Gmail,
能在同一个屏幕上同时看到收件箱
to view both the inbox and the actual email
和他们正在读的那封邮件。
that they were reading on the same screen.
他们为什么会这么要求？原因很简单，就是 Gmail 太慢了，
Now, why would they ask for that? Well, reason was simply that Gmail was too slow
用户不想等收件箱里每封邮件都加载出来。
and people did not want to wait to load each of the emails in the inbox.
他们想同时看到所有内容。
They want to see everything at the same time.
同样，在 Airbnb 早期，很多房客想拿到
Similarly, in early Airbnb, a lot of guests want to have the phone numbers of the
房东的电话号码，好打电话给他们。
host so they can call them.
我们心想，你们为什么需要这个？
We're like, why do you need that?
结果发现，是他们并不完全信任这个平台。
It just turned out that they didn't fully trust the platform.
就是说我们在 Airbnb 上没有展现出足够的信任感，
Like we had not displayed enough trust in Airbnb,
所以他们需要在真正下单前先了解房东，
so they needed to feel comfortable with getting to know the host
感到安心。其次，
before actually making the booking. Secondly,
用户对任何额外功能几乎都没有动力说不。
users don't have incentive to say no to really any additional features.
如果你问要不要这个功能、那个功能、另一个功能，
If you ask for this feature or this feature or this feature,
他们大概什么都会说要，对吧？
they'll probably say yes to everything, right?
但你才是负责排优先级的人，
You, however, are in charge of the prioritizations
而且你比他们更有动力去搞清楚
and you have a lot more incentives than they have to figure out
哪些功能才是最重要的。
which are the most important of the features.
那我们来聊聊下一步。
So let's talk about next steps.
假设你已经做了五到十次这样的用户访谈。
So you've done your five or 10 of these user interviews.
你也记好了笔记。我们来聊聊接下来该怎么做。
You've written down your notes. Let's let's talk about what you do then.
第一，确保你每一次访谈都有笔记。
1, you want to make sure you have notes from all each of the interviews.
你可以用便利贴或类似的软件来整理这些收获。
You can use sticky notes or some similar software to organize these learnings.
你可以把它们归到不同的类别里，
You can bucket them in different buckets
每一类对应不同的问题，然后看看
that kind of describes different problems and see
哪一个才是真正最重要的，
which one is actually the thing that matters the most
然后写下你的结论。
and then you want to write down your conclusions.
你从这一切中学到了什么？
What are you learning from all of this?
你要用所有这些信息，提出一个关于解决方案的假设，
You want to use all of this information to create a hypothesis of what the solution
猜测这个问题的解法可能是什么。别把这个过程想得太复杂。
to this problem might be. Don't over intellectualize this process.
其实，你只想尽快开始设计 MVP，
Really, you just want to start designing MVP as fast as you can,
但你要确保在决定 MVP 时手里有准确的信息
but you want to make sure you have accurate information when you decide the MVP
然后再用同一批用户去测试它
and then you want to test it with the same users.
弄清楚你要解决的问题是否真的有价值，也很重要
It's also important to know if the problem you're solving is actually valuable.
我的意思是，人们会看重这个问题的解决方案
What I mean by this is that people will value the solution to the problem
而且愿意为它付钱，或者说这个问题本身，解决它是有价值的
and enough to pay for it or the problem itself. Solving the problem is valuable.
下面是几个判断它是否有价值的好方法
So here are some good tips to determine if it is.
第一，现在有没有人为这个领域的其他解决方案付钱？
1, are people paying money for other solutions in the space today?
那些为碳排放核算做 PDF 报告的人
Are the people that make the PDF reports for carbon emissions accounting,
他们能拿到钱吗？
are they getting paid?
如果他们能拿到钱
Well, if they are getting paid,
那就是个好迹象，说明这大概是件有价值的事
that's a good sign that this is probably a valuable thing.
人们是不是已经有了解决这个问题的办法？
Do people already have solutions to this problem?
而且他们对现有办法很满意，哪怕在你看来很简陋，比如
They are very happy with, even though it might appear basics to you, for example,
像 Excel 或 Google 表格，其实是很多很多创业公司的竞争对手
like Excel or Google spreadsheets is actually competitors to many, many, many,
数以百计的创业公司，而且是相当强劲的对手
many hundreds of startups, actually quite a formidable one.
要让别人放弃 Excel 或 Google 表格
To move someone off Excel or Google spreadsheet,
你得让你方案的体验好上一大截
you need to make the experience of your solution dramatically better.
他们不会每月付你几百美元，去买一个
They're not going to pay you hundreds of dollars a month for something they can
用 Google 表格或 Excel 几乎一样轻松就能做的东西
almost as easily do in Google Spreadsheet or Excel.
第三，你要评估卖给这类人群有多容易
And 3, you want to evaluate how easy it is to sell to this audience.
这也是我很爱和合作的公司一起做的一件事
And this is one thing that I like to do a lot with the companies I work with.
比如，卖给水管工或承包商，出了名地比
For example, selling to plumbers or contractors is notoriously difficult compared to
卖给创业公司难
selling to startups.
前两类人很少更换他们的工具或软件
The first two groups just don't change their tools or the software very often,
而创业公司则随时愿意尝试新东西
versus startups are open to trying new things all the time.
所以就算你解决的问题很有价值
So if you are solving a problem that's valuable,
你还是得想想，卖给这类特定人群
you still have to think about whether it's going to be easy to sell to this
是否容易。一旦你有了 MVP 原型
particular audience. Once you have an MVP prototype,
你可以先把它拿给用户看
you can start by showing it to users,
哪怕它只是 InVision 之类做的设计原型
even if it's just a design prototype in envision or something like that.
你能直接点着走一遍
You can just click through.
我们在 Airbnb 时经常这么做
We used to do this at Airbnb all the time.
我们会下楼到办公室里，找一些人
We'd go downstairs in our in our office and we'd find some people
那些在等面试、或者在等咖啡之类的人
that were waiting for an interview or waiting for getting a coffee or something,
然后把 app 的最新版本拿给他们看
and we'd just show them the latest version of, of the app.
这会是我们手机上的一个 InVision 原型
This would be a envision prototype on our phone.
大概就是把手机递给他们，展示给他们看
It would be like hand them our phone and, and, and show it to them.
这些东西我们甚至还没做出来
This is stuff that we haven't even built yet.
用这个方法的关键，是不要告诉他们该怎么做
The key thing, if you're doing this tactic is to not tell them what to do.
不要告诉他们该怎么做，只要看着他们自己去摆弄
Do not tell them what to do. Just watch them play around with it.
你可以给他们一个具体目标，比如在 Airbnb 上订一次房，或者
You can tell them a specific goal like try to make a booking on Airbnb or try to do
在 Airbnb 上按日期搜索之类的
a search with dates on Airbnb or something like that,
但不要告诉他们每个界面到底该怎么操作
but do not tell them exactly how to solve each screen.
记住，如果这是个真实的产品
Remember, if this was a real product,
你不会站在他们旁边给他们出主意
you wouldn't be standing there next to them to give them advice.
做这件事时，还有一个好技巧
Another good trick when you're doing this,
无论你是在旁听，还是在录下他们的操作
either when you're listening or having them or recording them,
就是让他们边操作边把想法说出来
is to have them speak their mind while they're doing it,
让他们准确说出每一步在想什么
have them describe exactly what they're thinking on each of the steps.
也许是他们正在读的那些字
Maybe the words that they're reading,
也许这能提示你，哪些词他们看得懂
maybe that will give you hints of what words that they understand and
哪些词看不懂，或者某个界面是什么意思、有什么用
which words they don't understand or maybe what a specific screen means or what purpose is.
等你做完一批这样的访谈
And after you've done a bunch of these interviews
或许还有一些 MVP 原型测试环节之后
and then maybe MVP prototype sessions,
让这些受访者全程参与进来，是个很好的主意
it's a great idea to keep these interviewees involved throughout the process.
很多 YC 公司常用的一个做法是，建一个 Slack
One common idea that a lot of YC companies are using is to create a Slack instance
或者和客户建一个 WhatsApp 群
or a WhatsApp group with their customers.
你要让他们觉得自己很特别，对吧？
Now, you want to make them feel special, right?
你要让他们觉得自己能独家、实时地接触到那个未来的
You want to make them feel like they have exclusive active access to the future
会改变世界的产品。所以要想想你的措辞
world changing product. So think about how you are wording or, or,
或者你怎么告诉他们你要把他们拉进这个 WhatsApp 群。
or how you communicate this WhatsApp group that you're adding them to.
在开发推进过程中，持续把原型展示给他们看，是个很好的做法。
It's a great idea to keep showing them your prototype as they are progressing.
这样能给他们一种专属感，
Then kind of give them this exclusive feeling
觉得"我是第一个看到这个产品的人"，
that I'm the first one to see this product,
看着产品一路演进，也看着你在做。
product as it's progressing and also as you are.
根据他们说的话做出回应，你可以上线一个新的，
Reacting to things that they're saying you can ship a new,
一个新的界面、新的产品版本，
a new screen with a new version of the product and
这会建立起你和他们之间的信任。
that builds trust with it with them.
他们会知道，你对他们的反馈反应非常快。
They now know that you react to their feedback very fast.
最后，有些人会很喜欢认识跟他们做同样事情的人。
Finally, some of them will love connecting with other people doing the same thing as they are.
他们平时很少有这种机会，而你正是促成这件事的人。
They don't get to do this very often. And you are the one enabling that.
如果你做完这些步骤，就能从未来的用户那里收集到正确的信息。
If you do all these steps, you will collect the right information from your future users.
你会让他们持续参与进来，并把信息转化成……
You will keep them involved and translate information and
这能让你把信息转化成第一个原型和 MVP。
that allow you to translate information into a first prototype and MVP.
总结一下，这就是我今天讲的内容。
So to summarize, here's what I covered today.
为什么最好的创始人会在公司整个生命周期里都和用户交谈。
Why the best founders talk to the users throughout the lifetime of the company.
如何找到你的用户、如何和他们聊，问他们什么问题，
How to find your users and how to talk to them, what questions to ask them,
不该问什么，最后，如何把其中一些结论转化成一个 MVP。
what not to ask them, and finally, how to turn some of those conclusions into an MVP.
谢谢大家。
Thank you, everyone.